"Which Ultra-Processed Foods Drive
the Association with Death and Disease the Most?"
Even a small increase
in the consumption
of ultra-processed foods
is associated
with an increased risk
of developing several diseases.
And for each additional
daily serving,
the risk of dying prematurely
may increase by 2%.
Are there any babies we’d be
throwing out with the bathwater
if we avoided
ultra-processed foods?
Are there any that haven’t
been associated with disease?
It’s such a big category.
What we need are studies that
break it down and here we go.
The Framingham Offspring study:
Higher consumption
of ultra-processed foods
is associated
with increased risk
of cardiovascular disease.
But was it because
of the burgers or the bagels?
The link between
ultra-processed foods
and disease was largely driven
by the ultra-processed meat,
the sausage, bologna, salami,
hot dogs, and burgers.
Breakfast cereals, nearly all
of which are ultra-processed,
were associated with lower risk,
presumably
because cereal eaters
were eating less bacon and eggs.
In another US study,
this one 30 times larger,
researchers came
to the same conclusion.
The more ultra-processed,
the more cardiovascular disease.
But which ultra-processed foods?
Soft drinks,
both regular and diet,
and meat, specifically burgers,
fried chicken,
fried fish, and meat pizza.
Salty snacks like corn chips
and potato chips, and candy.
Ultra-processed food consumption
and high blood pressure
driven mostly by soda and meat.
If we excluded soda and meat,
would there still
be an association
between ultra-processed foods
and cardiovascular disease?
We can turn to the three big
Harvard cohorts.
200,000 people followed
for decades.
And yes, total intake
of ultra-processed foods
is associated with
cardiovascular risk,
but that was driven
by soda and meat.
Sugar-sweetened beverages
and processed red meat,
poultry and fish,
like fish sticks.
What if we exclude soda
and meat?
The relationship between
ultra-processed foods
and cardiovascular disease
disappears.
So, nutritional advice
for cardiovascular health
should consider
the differential consequences
of group-specific
ultra-processed foods
and specifically, that means
soft drinks and processed meats
should be discouraged.
You know what else
is an ultra-processed food?
Vodka.
So, when you look
at food processing
and cancer risk,
if you exclude alcoholic drinks,
all of a sudden,
the link between processed foods
and a number of cancers
becomes insignificant,
suggesting that it was probably
the alcohol driving
those associations.
Though for colorectal
cancer risk, soda,
and ready-to-eat foods
like pizza,
and ready-to-eat meat, poultry,
and fish,
may also be playing a role.
For pancreatic cancer,
the association between
ultra-processed foods
and pancreatic cancer
was really more
just an association with foods
like donuts, cakes, cookies,
and meat and meat products.
Diabetes.
You can see the straight line
increase in diabetes risk
with increasing
ultra-processed food intake,
but not all
ultra-processed foods:
mostly animal-based products
and the pizza category again.
What about mortality?
Those with the most
ultra-processed food consumption
had a higher risk of dying
from all causes put together,
but it mattered
what kinds of foods.
Ready-to-eat red meat, poultry,
and seafood products
had particularly strong
associations with mortality.
The worst ultra-processed food
when it came to dying
prematurely in general,
meat, poultry, seafood.
The worst when it comes to dying
from cancer,
meat, poultry, seafood.
The worst when it comes to dying
from cardiovascular disease,
meat, poultry, seafood.
The worst when it comes to dying
from lung disease,
like Emphysema,
meat, poultry seafood.
The worst when it comes to dying
from neurodegenerative diseases,
ice cream.
And the worst when it comes
to dying from other causes,
meat, poultry, seafood.
The bottom line
is that the major factors
contributing
to the harmful influence
of ultra-processed foods
on mortality
are soda and processed meat,
including poultry and fish.
That’s what a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of all such studies showed:
higher mortality associated
with drinking
more sugar sweetened beverages
like soda, including diet soda,
and eating more processed meat,
or eating any processed meat
at all.
So, the ultra-processed
foods problem may really
just be a soda and meat problem.
There was one ray of sunshine
in this study, though.
The researchers found one
ultra-processed dessert
that was associated
with lower mortality-
dark chocolate.